<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<chapter id="developers">
  <title>Media Explorer for developers</title>

  <section id="developers-architecture">
    <title>Architecture</title>

    <para>Media Explorer is a single project, but it is composed of
    several interrelated libraries and applications. The points
    below explain these parts and where they live in the source
    tree:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>libmex</emphasis> is a library
        containing the <link linked="developers-works-mvc">MVC
        framework</link>, plugin framework, generic widgets, and other
        components used by the UX.</para>

        <para>It lives in the <filename>mex</filename> directory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Media Explorer</emphasis> is the application,
        built with the libmex library. Note that the libmex
        classes could be used to build alternative UXs: see
        <link linkend="developers-works-classes">this diagram</link>
        for a (very) high-level overview of the classes available.</para>

        <para>It lives in the <filename>shell</filename> directory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis>player</emphasis> (in a directory with the
        same name) exposes the Media Explorer player over DBus. The
        core functionality is documented in
        <link linkend="MexMediaDBUSBridge"><type>MexMediaDBUSBridge</type></link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <filename>plugins</filename> directory (in the
        source code) contains various Media Explorer plugins, which
        extend the functionality of the basic libmex library.</para>

        <para>This is where the
        <link linkend="developers-works-content">Media Explorer Tracker
        plugin</link> lives (in the <filename>tracker</filename>
        directory).</para>

        <para>Search and queue are also implemented as plugins, also
        in this directory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Media Explorer also integrates with various other libraries
    and services, as described in
    <link linkend="developers-architecture-integration">this
    section</link>.</para>

    <section id="developers-architecture-integration">
      <title>Integration points with other libraries and services</title>

      <para>Media Explorer was designed to integrate smoothly with
      the MeeGo software stack. Consequently, there are
      a number of points where Media Explorer integrates with
      other libraries and services; see
      <link linkend="developers-architecture-integration-diagram">this
      diagram</link> for an overview (as seen by
      <command>jhbuild dot</command>).</para>

      <mediaobject id="developers-architecture-integration-diagram">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="dependencies.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <alt>
          <para>Library dependencies for Media Explorer</para>
        </alt>
      </mediaobject>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><ulink url="http://gupnp.org/">GUPnP</ulink></title>

            <para>This is part of the standard MeeGo UPnP stack. It is a
            low-level implementation that provides the raw UPnP protocol:
            it has no APIs for higher-level specifications such as MediaServer:1.</para>
          </formalpara>

          <para><ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Rygel">Rygel</ulink> (also part
          of MeeGo) is available as a ContentDirectory implementation for
          sharing media to other devices. However, this is not used at
          present.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><ulink url="http://projects.gnome.org/tracker/">Tracker</ulink></title>

            <para>This is Media Explorer's metadata store. It holds
            metadata for both local and removable media, as well
            as caching data about any UPnP servers discovered. Local
            and removable media is indexed using standard Tracker
            methods.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Grilo">Grilo</ulink></title>

            <para>This is a media discovery and metadata aggregation
            library which abstracts content browsing and searching. By
            default, Media Explorer uses Grilo to enable browsing and
            searching of local files and content on UPnP
            servers.</para>
          </formalpara>

          <para>Configuring other Grilo plugins can enable access to further
          content sources: see <link linkend="users-content-discovery">the section
          about configuring Grilo plugins</link> for more details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/">GStreamer</ulink></title>

            <para>The media player is a GStreamer-based daemon with a
            DBus API. It uses the GStreamer <type>playbin2</type>
            element for playback, so hardware acceleration is used if
            suitable elements are installed.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/dbus">DBus</ulink></title>

            <para>The media player exposes a DBus API to other
            applications.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><ulink url="http://clutter-project.org">Clutter</ulink></title>

            <para>Clutter is a low-level drawing toolkit which abstracts and
            simplifies the OpenGL API. Clutter doesn't mandate a particular
            look and feel: this is provided by toolkits built on top of Clutter
            (like Mx, see below).</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><ulink url="http://git.clutter-project.org/mx/">Mx</ulink></title>

            <para>Mx is a high-level toolkit built on top of Clutter.
            It provides an application model and a variety of widgets
            such as buttons, dialogs and toolbars.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>While Media Explorer was designed with MeeGo in mind,
        it is perfectly possible to build and run it on other
        distributions (e.g. Fedora). However, bear in mind that it
        uses some libraries which may either be unavailable for
        your distro (e.g. Mx, Grilo) or at versions which are too old
        (e.g. DBus, Tracker). If your distro is too outdated,
        one solution is to build Media Explorer with jhbuild:
        <link linkend="developers-extending-environment">this
        section</link> explains how.</para>
      </note>

    </section>

    <section id="developers-ux">
      <title>User experience design</title>

      <section id="developers-ux-input">
        <title>Input device</title>

        <para>The input device is expected to have a 5-way d-pad
        (up/down/left/right/activate), back, information and home keys. These
        are the primary navigation keys, and are all that is required to
        use the majority of the UX. The remote is also expected to
        have a full alphanumeric keyboard, used for searching and in the
        web browser.</para>

        <para>Because the UX doesn't support a mouse pointer,
        UX elements are activated by navigating to the element and
        pressing the activate button.</para>

        <para>On a netbook, the inputs are mapped onto the keyboard
        as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>up/down/left/right = cursor keys</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>activate (a.k.a. ok) = return key</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>back = <keycap>Esc</keycap> key</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>information = right-click key
            (on my keyboard, it looks like a context menu)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>home = the "Windows" key</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Output device</title>

        <para>720p is the only supported video mode. The display will be
        configured for the best mode approximating 720p, and if this
        isn't possible an error message will be displayed.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Views</title>

        <para>The majority of the UX is based around two styles of view:
        <emphasis>panel</emphasis> and <emphasis>grid</emphasis>.</para>

        <para><emphasis>A panel view</emphasis> displays a number of
        panels (as columns across the screen); each has a header which
        can be activated to "drill down" from the summary to a more
        detailed view (another panel view or a grid view) showing a
        limited number of items (generally 8). Typically these items are
        the most relevant or recent. The remaining items are accessed by
        activating the panel heading, which changes the UX to show a grid
        view. When an item is activated, relevant metadata for the item
        and actions associated with it are displayed.</para>

        <para><emphasis>A grid view</emphasis> fills the screen with
        items and can be scrolled vertically. All of the items are
        included, and there is no implicit filtering.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Home screen</title>

        <para>The home screen is a panel view, with columns for
        <guilabel>Search</guilabel>, <guilabel>Video</guilabel>,
        <guilabel>Photo</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Queue</guilabel>.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><guilabel>Search</guilabel></title>
              <para>This is used to search all available media,
              i.e. local files, UPnP servers, Vimeo
              and so on.</para>
            </formalpara>

            <para>Search history is stored and presented to
            the user if available. Search results are presented in
            panels, organised by source; a user can drill down from
            any panel to a grid view of relevant results.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><guilabel>Video</guilabel></title>
              <para>This displays available video content.</para>
            </formalpara>

            <para>Drilling down from the home screen will take you to the
            source view, where each source is another panel showing
            the 8 most recent videos from that source. Drilling
            down from the source panel will open the grid view,
            where all the content items from that source are visually
            presented as thumbnails. Any folder hierarchy is flattened
            and the content can be sorted in various ways.</para>

            <para>If there is only one source, drilling down from the
            home screen will go directly to the grid view.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><guilabel>Photos</guilabel></title>

              <para>Very similar to <guilabel>Video</guilabel>, but
              for still images. There are different controls available
              when viewing images, for example starting a slideshow or
              rotating the image.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><guilabel>Queue</guilabel></title>

              <para>A queue of content to be played can be created by
              activating the items and selecting <guilabel>Add to
              Queue</guilabel>.</para>
            </formalpara>

            <para>If the item is already in a queue, this action
            becomes <guilabel>Remove from Queue</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Playback</title>

        <para>When playing back media, the metaphor is that the controls
        and information are "below" the screen. These are arranged in
        rows; a user can navigate between the rows with the up
        and down keys. Specific controls in each row are
        traversed by using the left and right keys.</para>

        <para>For videos, pressing the down key will slide up the pause
        and stop controls; pressing down again will slide up the seek
        bar; and again will bring up the <guilabel>Related Content</guilabel>
        list.</para>

        <para>The <guilabel>Related Content</guilabel> row lists
        content that is related to the current content. If the media is
        from a directory, it lists media in the same directory; if from
        a search, the other results; and so on. This area could also
        be used to show recommended content or advertising.</para>

        <para>For photos, the controls are different (rotate buttons,
        no seek bar, etc). Pressing up will slide these off the screen,
        resulting in just the photo being visible.</para>
      </section>


      <section>
        <title>Media information</title>

        <para>At any time in the Media Explorer, you can get
        information about the current displayed media or the
        currently selected media by pressing the info key.</para>
      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="developers-works">
    <title>How it works</title>

    <para>This section contains various nitty gritty explanations
    about how Media Explorer is put together.</para>

    <section id="developers-works-mvc">
      <title>MVC</title>

      <para>Media Explorer is broadly based on a Model-View-Controller
      architecture.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Model: Media Explorer has a single <emphasis>root model</emphasis>
          (an instance of <type>MexAggregateModel</type>). A plugin loaded
          by Media Explorer's plugin manager can push models, each associated
          with a category, into the root model. A model pushed by a plugin can
          be a simple <type>MexModel</type> or another <type>MexAggregateModel
          </type>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>View: The top-level view element is an <type>MexExplorer</type>
          instance. This is a horizontally-expanding, single-row
          <type>MexResizingHBox</type>, filled with <type>MexColumns</type>;
          a new column is added each time a new model is added to the explorer;
          the column title is set to the model's category. Focus moves
          between columns in response to UI events (e.g. key presses).</para>

          <para>The columns are populated via the controller classes
          (see below).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Controller: A <type>MexContentProxy</type> instance
          (an implementation of <type>MexProxy</type>) is responsible
          for generating UI elements for each model. Each time a new
          model is added to the explorer, a new column is created, and
          an <type>MxWidget</type> generated and added to the column
          for each <type>MexContent</type> item in the model (currently
          hard-coded to a maximum of 10 items per column).</para>

          <para>The default behaviour is for each content item to be
          represented by a <type>MexContentBox</type>. This is an
          expanding widget which displays one line of the content item's
          title, expanding on click to display the full title.</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <link linkend="developers-works-classes-diagram">class
      hierarchy diagram</link>in the next section should help you
      identify how the classes mentioned above relate to each other; the
      API reference gives more detail about the specific methods
      supported by each class/interface.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="developers-works-classes">
      <title>Class hierarchy</title>

      <para>The <link linkend="developers-works-classes-diagram">diagram
      below</link> shows libmex's class hierarchy.</para>

      <mediaobject id="developers-works-classes-diagram">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="classes.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <alt>
          <para>The libmex class hierarchy</para>
        </alt>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>

    <section id="developers-works-content">
      <title>Content discovery</title>

      <para>Media Explorer enables browsing, discovery and playback of
      media content; to do this, it needs to have media sources available.
      The Grilo framework for media discovery and browsing is used to provide
      those media sources.</para>

      <para>Grilo provides a uniform API for accessing content
      and its metadata. Several Grilo plugins exist for adapting media
      for well-known sources (Vimeo, Flickr, YouTube etc.) so they can be
      presented via the Grilo API.</para>

      <para>However, due to various licensing issues, these plugins are not
      enabled by default in Media Explorer. The only plugin which
      is enabled is <emphasis>grilo-tracker</emphasis>. This uses
      a Tracker service, running in the same environment as
      Media Explorer, to make media indexed by Tracker
      available through the Grilo API.</para>

      <para>Tracker itself is a collection of data mining and indexing
      services, typically used for searching the local filesystem. By
      default Tracker comes with several indexing services called
      <emphasis>miners</emphasis>. The most widely used miner is the
      filesystem miner, responsible for indexing local files.
      Media Explorer makes use of the <emphasis>UPnP</emphasis> miner,
      if available, which additionally indexes <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_Plug_and_Play">UPnP</ulink>
      servers.</para>

      <para>The diagram below gives a high-level overview of the
      components involved:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="content-discovery.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <alt>
          <para>Content discovery components in Media Explorer</para>
        </alt>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The arrows between the nodes in the diagram represent
      media data from UPnP servers and the local filesystem being
      scanned, indexed and presented by higher-level components.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Debugging content discovery</title>

        <para>This section gives a few tips about how to check that
        everything is working properly in the content discovery stack.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Check tracker is indexing</title>

              <para>You can follow the status of Tracker and its miners
              from the command line with:</para>
            </formalpara>

            <informalexample>
              <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <command>tracker-control -FS</command>
              </screen>
            </informalexample>

            <para>The output should look something like this:</para>

            <informalexample>
              <screen>
Store:
06 Apr 2011, 14:54:52:  ✓     Idle

Miners:
06 Apr 2011, 14:54:52:  ✓     UPnP                  - Idle (ESMITH5-MOBL1: esmith5:)
06 Apr 2011, 14:54:52:  ✓     File System           - Idle
06 Apr 2011, 14:54:52:  ✓     Applications          - Idle
Press Ctrl+C to end follow of Tracker state
              </screen>
            </informalexample>

            <para>Note that the UPnP miner is reporting the ID
            of a Windows laptop running Windows Media Center (which
            is UPnP compatible).</para>

            <para>If a miner has an "X" against it, there may
            be something wrong with Tracker's configuration.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Check Tracker is indexing the right directories</title>

              <para>If your local media aren't showing up in
              Media Explorer, it may be that they aren't being indexed
              by Tracker.</para>
            </formalpara>

            <para>Check that Tracker is indexing directories
            where some media exists: see
            <link linkend="users-configuring">these instructions</link>
            for configuring Tracker.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem id="developers-works-content-grilo-test-ui">
            <formalpara>
              <title>Check Grilo can browse your media</title>

              <para>Tracker's directory settings might look right,
              but media may still not appear in Media Explorer.
              In this case, ensure that Tracker has actually indexed your
              media using the <command>grilo-test-ui</command>
              command. This runs a basic Grilo media browsing
              interface:</para>
            </formalpara>

            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                             fileref="grilo-test-ui-screenshot.png" />
                </imageobject>
                <alt>
                  <para><command>grilo-test-ui</command> showing
                  local media available through Grilo</para>
                </alt>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>

            <para>If your media files have been indexed, they should
            show up in this interface. If not, Grilo is probably
            failing to communicate with Tracker correctly.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Check detailed logs for Tracker, Grilo and GUPnP</title>

              <para>If you haven't identified the issue by following
              the above steps, you can enable more verbose logging
              for the various Media Explorer components as follows:</para>
            </formalpara>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Tracker</title>
                  <para>Set this environment variable:</para>
                </formalpara>

                <para><code>TRACKER_VERBOSITY=3</code></para>

                <para>This turns on all debug messages.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Grilo</title>

                  <para>Set this environment variable:</para>
                </formalpara>

                <para><code>GRL_DEBUG=*:debug</code></para>

                <para>NB this produces <emphasis>a lot</emphasis> of
                messages; other less verbose debug levels are available
                (see the Grilo API docs).</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>GUPnP</title>

                  <para>Set this environment variable:</para>
                </formalpara>

                <para><code>GUPNP_DEBUG=true</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="developers-works-events">
      <title>Binding keys to actions</title>

      <para>Media Explorer is designed to function as a netbook application
      or as a UX for a dedicated media centre distribution. This means
      that the UX is entirely usable without a mouse. However, it also
      means that it may be used with input devices other than a keyboard
      (such as a TV remote control). On top of this, the application
      may also run in environments where a full X environment is not
      available (for example, where the application is on a different
      GDL plane from the X server, as might happen when running
      on a processor like
      <ulink url="http://download.intel.com/design/celect/downloads/ce3100-product-brief.pdf">Intel's
      CE3100</ulink>).</para>

      <section>
        <title>Terminology and definitions</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>evdev</title>
              <para>The "protocol" which reports events from the
              kernel to userspace. At its core, this "protocol" is
              reading a well-defined structure from a file descriptor
              obtained by opening a <filename>/dev/input/event/*</filename>
              file.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>xorg-input-evdev</title>
              <para>The Xorg input driver to feed X with evdev
              events.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>lirc</title>
              <para>Since the 2.6.36 kernel, lirc, a set of
              InfraRed device drivers, has been integrated into the
              mainline and lirc devices are exposed as evdev devices.
              This means that the issue of handling infra-red controls
              is now reduced to the issue of handling evdev devices.
              (Previously, binding key events would have involved
              handling IR devices and evdev devices separately.)</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>key code (keycode)</title>
              <para>A number assigned to the physical key. These days,
              on linux, these are defined in &lt;linux/input.h&gt;
              and are part of evdev key event structures.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>key symbol (keysym)</title>
              <para>The logical symbol associated with the keycode.
              For instance, 'a' is associated with the keycode 38. On
              standard linux desktops, Xorg is responsible for the
              mapping between keycodes and keysyms.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>libxkbcommon</title>
              <para>This library provides control over the keyboard, extending
              the basic facilities available in X. The project has a
              <ulink url="http://cgit.freedesktop.org/xorg/lib/libxkbcommon">public
              git repo</ulink>.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The trouble with input device keys</title>

        <para>Because Media Explorer is a media browser and player, it
        may be used in contexts outside the traditional netbook or laptop.
        This in turn means that users may want to control it with
        input devices beyond the standard mouse and keyboard, such as
        TV remote controls, for example:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>keyboards, even ones with all those fancy "Internet
            keys"</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>remotes that are seen as USB HID devices</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>IR remotes exposed as evdev devices via in-kernel lirc</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>However, given the variety of input devices, a couple of
        issues arise:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Some Media Explorer actions (show more info. about
            some content, select some content etc.) naturally map to a
            a user's experience with modern TVs, DVD players,
            CD players, portable music players etc. In turn, a user
            can map those actions onto typical remote control keys
            (in the above case, onto <guilabel>Info</guilabel> and
            <guilabel>OK</guilabel> respectively).</para>

            <para>However, these keys don't always have natural equivalents
            on a standard computer keyboard; but a user with a standard
            keyboard should still be able to control Media Explorer. So
            there needs to be some way to map actions (and their
            keys on a remote control) onto standard keyboard keys.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>While remote controls are familiar to users, they
            bring a different set of issues when applied to a UX in
            a traditional Linux environment. Some of the keys on a TV
            remote, when pressed, produce events with keycodes greater
            than 255; however, these events are ignored by X, the
            window manager likely to be used on Linux. In some
            cases, remote control keys even produce keycodes which don't
            have <emphasis>any</emphasis> keysym under X.</para>

            <para>In this case, these exotic keycodes need to be mapped
            onto keysyms which X does recognise.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="developers-works-plugins">
      <title>Plugin management and configuration</title>

      <para>Media Explorer plugins are packaged as standard shared-object
      libraries or modules. They are then installed into one of the plugin
      directories for Media Explorer, namely:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <filename>$INSTALL_PREFIX/lib/mex/plugins</filename>
          </para>

          <para>This is the main directory where most plugins are
          installed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <filename>$USER_CONFIG_DIR/mex/plugins</filename>
          </para>

          <para><filename>$USER_CONFIG_DIR</filename> defaults
          to <filename>$HOME/.config</filename> on freedesktop.org
          compliant distros (like MeeGo). Could be used for user-specific
          plugins.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <filename>$CURRENT_WORKING_DIRECTORY/plugins</filename>
          </para>

          <para><filename>$CURRENT_WORKING_DIRECTORY</filename> is
          the directory from where <command>mex</command> is
          being run.</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Responsibility for finding and loading plugins lies with the
      <type>MexPluginManager</type>, assigned as a member variables of the
      Media Explorer application. Plugin loading works like this:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><command>mex</command> creates a plugin manager
          (an instance of <type>MexPluginManager</type>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The plugin manager looks for <filename>.so</filename> and
          <filename>.la</filename> files in the <emphasis>plugin
          directories</emphasis>. (See above for details of where they
          are.)</para>

          <para>For each matching plugin file in those directories, the plugin manager
          does the following:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Loads the file via GModule.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Looks for a <function>mex_get_plugin_type</function>
              symbol in the module's symbol table.</para>

              <para>If the <function>mex_get_plugin_type</function> symbol
              is found, the plugin manager creates an instance of the plugin
              class and puts a reference to it into its plugin list. It
              also emits a <constant>plugin-loaded</constant> signal.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Media Explorer responds to the plugin load (through a handler
          attached to the <constant>plugin-loaded</constant> signal)
          according to the type of plugin:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>ModelProvider: The models provided by the plugin are
              added into Media Explorer's root model.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>ToolProvider: The tool is added to the tool area
              of the interface; when the tool is activated, e.g. by a
              key press, the <type>ClutterActor</type> associated with
              the tool is presented. This actor can replace some or all
              of the Media Explorer UI with its own "sub-interface".</para>

              <para>For example, the Media Explorer search plugin is
              a ToolProvider: when activated, it presents a "search page", with
              a text entry widget for entering a search string and
              an auto-suggest column. The search page replaces the other
              panels in the user interface.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>ActionProvider: The actions provided by the plugin
              are added to Media Explorer's <type>MexActionManager</type>.</para>

              <para>Actions are "things you can do to a piece of content".
              Media Explorer displays the actions for a piece of content
              when you press the information key while that content
              is highlighted. For example, <command>Watch</command> or
              <command>Add to queue</command> for a video, and
              <command>View</command> for a picture.</para>

              <para>An ActionProvider plugin can add new actions to
              particular pieces of content. Each action is defined by an
              <type>MexActionInfo</type> object returned by the provider;
              this object specifies the MIME types for which an action is
              applicable, as well as the action itself (an instance
              of <type>MxAction</type>).</para>
            </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>See <link linkend="developers-extending">the section
      about extending Media Explorer</link> for more information on plugin
      development.</para>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="developers-extending">
    <title>Extending Media Explorer</title>

    <para>This section explains how to add your own extensions and
    customisations to Media Explorer.</para>

    <section id="developers-extending-need-to-know">
      <title>What you need to know</title>

      <para>What you need to know to extend Media Explorer can be
      summarised as "be a GNOME developer": most of the technologies
      you need to know are used in the GNOME project.</para>

      <para>But, more specifically, you need to know:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to use
          <ulink url="https://live.gnome.org/Jhbuild">jhbuild</ulink>. This
          is the easiest way to build a working development
          environment for Media Explorer (see
          <link linkend="developers-extending-environment">below</link>).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to use autotools (to put together a plugin
          project)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to code in C (to be able to write in a language which
          integrates with the Media Explorer app)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to use GObject (to be able to subclass libmex
          classes to slot into Media Explorer)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>How to write applications using Clutter+Mx (optional and
          not vital): to provide custom widgets for your plugin</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>

    <section id="developers-extending-environment">
      <title>Setting up a development environment</title>

      <para>The easiest way to work on Media Explorer is to use
      <emphasis>jhbuild-mex</emphasis>. This can build
      all the correct dependencies for Media Explorer, providing
      you are working on a relatively recent Linux distro (e.g. Debian
      sid or Fedora 14). You can get it from ???TODO. Installation
      and Media Explorer build instructions are included in that
      project.</para>

      <para>Once you've installed jhbuild-mex and built
      Media Explorer, you can make local modifications to the Media
      Explorer source from inside a jhbuild-mex shell, e.g.</para>

      <informalexample>
        <screen>
# work directly on the checked-out jhbuild source; see
# <link linkend="developers-extending-environment-warning">below</link> for caveats
<prompt>$</prompt> <command>cd $JHBUILD_MEX_SOURCE/media-explorer</command>
<prompt>$</prompt> <command>git co -b my-shiny-new-branch</command>

# ...edit source code and make local commits using your editor of choice...

<prompt>$</prompt> <command>jhbuild-mex shell</command>
<prompt>$</prompt> <command>make</command>

# to install your version of mex over the stock version
<prompt>$</prompt> <command>make install</command>
        </screen>
      </informalexample>

      <para>You only need to be inside the jhbuild-mex shell when
      you want to build the source; but it's often easiest to just stay
      inside a shell all the time so you don't forget to
      switch before building.</para>

      <warning id="developers-extending-environment-warning">
        <para>If you run <command>jhbuild-mex build</command> after
        making modifications to the source, your branch will be used
        as the basis for the build. So if you are working on your
        own branch, you will need to merge any changes made
        to mex master into your own branches yourself.</para>

        <para>You should also be aware that if you choose to clear
        the source directory during a <command>jhbuild-mex</command>
        build (one of the options if a module fails to build), any
        local changes you've made could be lost. So it's a good idea
        to push your own branches to a remote git server as a backup.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>Another useful tool is <command>turbine</command>, which
      provides a GUI for creating GObject classes. This can help a lot when
      writing Media Explorer plugins (which are, naturally, GObject classes).
      You can get turbine from
      <ulink url="http://git.gnome.org/browse/turbine/">GNOME git</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="developers-extending-building">
      <title>Enabling and configuring content sources</title>

      <para>The default jhbuild-mex configuration builds a minimal
      version of the application and its support libraries, with most of
      the Grilo plugins disabled (for various licensing reasons). This
      means that you can't make use of Grilo to feed media from
      other sources like Flickr, YouTube and Vimeo into Media
      Explorer.</para>

      <para>However, you can re-enable Grilo plugins by changing the
      default configure options, then adding the plugins to the Media Explorer
      search whitelist. Then, providing the user supplies the
      necessary API keys, results from these extra sources should
      appear in Media Explorer's search results display.</para>

      <section id="developers-extending-building-enabling-grilo">
        <title>Enabling Grilo plugins</title>

        <para>The following Grilo plugins can provide search results
        to Media Explorer:</para>

        <itemizedlist id="developers-extending-building-enabling-grilo-list">
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>jamendo</title>
              <para>For accessing free music from
              <ulink url="http://www.jamendo.com/">Jamendo</ulink>.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>upnp</title>
              <para>For accessing media on UPnP servers. Although
              grilo-tracker + tracker-upnp (both enabled in
              Media Explorer by default) provide access to UPnP
              media, the Grilo UPnP plugin is an alternative way to
              index UPnP media. It may be useful if you are using
              Media Explorer on a system where Tracker isn't
              available.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>vimeo</title>
              <para>For accesing videos on
              <ulink url="http://vimeo.com/">Vimeo</ulink>.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>youtube</title>
              <para>For accessing videos on
              <ulink url="http://youtube.com">YouTube</ulink>.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>flickr</title>
              <para>For accessing photos on
              <ulink url="http://flickr.com/">Flickr</ulink>.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <!--listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>apple-trailers</title>
              <para>this doesn't currently work due to an issue
              with user agents</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem-->

        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>Grilo has various other plugins, and doubtless more
          will be added over time, but the ones listed above are the
          only ones which affect Media Explorer searches.</para>
        </note>

        <para>You can set configure options for the build via jhbuild-mex
        by editing the <filename>$HOME/.jhbuildrc-mex-custom</filename>
        file. Add a line to customise the arguments passed to
        <command>autogen.sh</command>; this in turn affects how
        <command>configure</command> is invoked.</para>

        <para>For example, to turn on the vimeo and youtube plugins, the line
        would look like this:</para>

        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>
module_autogenargs['grilo-plugins'] = '--enable-upnp --enable-vimeo'
          </programlisting>
        </informalexample>

        <para>To enable other modules, append <code>--enable-$MODULE</code>
        to the autogenargs string, where <code>$MODULE</code> is one
        of the module names from
        <link linkend="developers-extending-building-grilo-plugins">this
        list</link>.</para>

        <para>It's also possible to disable a plugin. You might want to
        do this if a plugin is causing Media Explorer to crash (as the
        YouTube plugin has done on occasion in the past). To do this,
        just pass <code>--disable-$MODULE</code> as an autogen argument.
        For example, to enable upnp and vimeo but disable youtube:</para>

        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>
module_autogenargs['grilo-plugins'] = '--enable-upnp \
                                       --enable-vimeo \
                                       --disable-youtube'
          </programlisting>
        </informalexample>

      </section>

      <section id="developers-extending-building-whitelisting">
        <title>Whitelisting Grilo plugins</title>

        <para>Once a Grilo plugin has been enabled, the next step is
        to allow Media Explorer to use it as a content source. Once
        you've done this, any searches made through the Media Explorer
        interface will also search the enabled content
        sources (as well as the local filesystem and UPnP via the
        grilo-tracker plugin).</para>

        <para>To enable a Grilo plugin as a Media Explorer content
        source, modify your <filename>$HOME/.config/mex/mex.conf</filename>
        configuration file (create this file if it doesn't exist). Here's
        an example:</para>

        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>
[grilo-plugins]
enabled=grl-tracker;grl-vimeo;grl-flickr;grl-jamendo
          </programlisting>
        </informalexample>

        <para>Note that the plugin ID is a name shown in
        <link linkend="developers-extending-building-enabling-grilo-list">the
        previous list</link>, prefixed with <code>grl</code>. You
        can enable more plugins by appending a semi-colon and a plugin
        ID to the value for <varname>enabled</varname>.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Once you've enabled new plugins in Grilo and whitelisted
          them, you may still need to configure them by following
          <link linkend="users-content-sources">these
          instructions</link>.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section id="developers-extending-building-checking">
        <title>Checking which Grilo plugins are enabled</title>

        <para>You can test which Grilo plugins are available
        by running <command>mex</command> from inside a jhbuild-mex
        shell, with Grilo registry debugging turned on. Use the
        <envar>GRL_DEBUG</envar> environment variable to control
        which messages Grilo displays, and at which log levels.
        Full debugging for the plugin registry is enabled like this:</para>

        <informalexample>
          <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <command>GRL_DEBUG=plugin-registry:debug mex</command>
          </screen>
        </informalexample>

        <para>A plugin logs a message like this if it loads
        successfully:</para>

        <informalexample>
          <screen>
<![CDATA[
(mex:31977): Grilo-DEBUG: [plugin-registry] grl-plugin-registry.c:173: Plugin rank 'grl-jamendo' : 0
(mex:31977): Grilo-DEBUG: [plugin-registry] grl-plugin-registry.c:370: New source available: 'grl-jamendo'
(mex:31977): Grilo-DEBUG: [plugin-registry] grl-plugin-registry.c:577: Loaded plugin 'grl-jamendo' from '/home/ell/mex/install/lib/grilo-0.1/libgrljamendo.so'
]]>
          </screen>
        </informalexample>

        <para>Make sure you have
        <link linkend="users-grilo-configuration">configured the
        plugins</link> first: any plugins which require configuration
        but don't have it report a failure like this:</para>

        <informalexample>
          <screen>
<![CDATA[
(mex:31866): Grilo-DEBUG: [plugin-registry] grl-plugin-registry.c:173: \
  Plugin rank 'grl-vimeo' : 0

(mex:31866): Grilo-WARNING **: [vimeo] grl-vimeo.c:103: Missing configuration

(mex:31866): Grilo-WARNING **: [plugin-registry] grl-plugin-registry.c:551: \
  Failed to initialize plugin: './../lib/grilo-0.1/libgrlvimeo.so'
]]>
          </screen>
        </informalexample>

        <para>Finally, confirm that the Grilo plugin is supplying
        content to Media Explorer by performing a search. Check that
        the search results contain columns for the plugins you've enabled.
        For example,
        <link linkend="developers-extending-building-checking-screenshot">this
        screenshot</link> shows results being returned from Jamendo,
        Flickr, Tracker (local filesystem and UPnP), and Vimeo:</para>

        <screenshot id="developers-extending-building-checking-screenshot">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="search-results.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <alt>
              <para>Search showing results from Jamendo, Flickr,
              Tracker (local filesystem and UPnP), and Vimeo</para>
            </alt>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>
